各位貴賓,發表記者會在過五分鐘之後即將正式開始,請您記得將手機轉為震動或靜音。
各位現場以及線上的貴賓大家早安,歡迎參加消除對婦女一切形式歧視公約第五次國家報告國際審查會議結論性意見與建議發表記者會。
Gender equality is not only a fundamental human right but also the core and driving force behind Taiwan's deepening democracy progress.
The successful completion of this review meeting marks a milestone toward an even more mature national reporting system for women's human rights in our country.
We pledge to implement the spirit of CEDAW with unwavering resolve and to continuously leverage the combined power of the government and civil society to advance our systems, execute policies, respond to public sentiments, and align with international standards.
Moving forward, I will personally supervise all ministries and agencies to ensure they actively implement the concluding observations and recommendations.
In closing, I would like to express my gratitude once again to all the experts for assisting in the review of this national report and to all government agencies, non-NGOs, and distinguished guests for your joint participation.
Wish you all good health and every success in your future endeavors. Thank you very much.
And now we move on to the presentation of concluding observations and recommendations over to the International Review Committee. Madam Chair, please.
Thank you. Your Excellency, the Honorable Minister, and all of the distinguished guests that we have from the different line ministries, the civil society organization, and members of the press, good morning.
Well, on behalf of the International Review Committee, I would like to start by extending profound appreciation to the government of Taiwan first for the opportunity to engage in this unique global process.
The independent peer review by Taiwan is a global model that many countries are still grappling with how to replicate.
And so the dedication, the commitment, the consistency that we have witnessed over the years is what I would first like to salute, to thank you for keeping faith with CEDAW.
And I believe that the findings that we will be sharing today, myself and my colleagues, are things that you will find encouraging as a society.
I believe that 15 years following your adoption of CEDAW and enactments and enforcement of the law, of the CEDAW Enforcement Act, the society has grown tremendously.
I have taken time to look at the size of the economy, women's labor rate participation, and women's level of education and engagement in different sectors, as well as the services that are provided by ministries, departments, and agencies.
I really would like to commend and congratulate the government of Taiwan for the effort, the resources that has been invested.
And I believe that as your society transforms, the gains, the economic gains would help you to continue to rise higher and higher in the global development index.
As we mentioned during the opening ceremony, ranking sixth globally on the Human Rights Gender Index is not a joke.
It's not a small feat.
It has taken a lot of collaboration, collective work, and expanding the capacity of both the vulnerable and the weak in the society to contribute to national development.
That is the goal of CEDAW.
And over the past five days, because today is the fifth day, we have had the opportunity to have open and frank conversation with you.
And I can tell you that my colleagues will talk about some sectors, but what we see is increasing levels of accountability across the society, across the different agencies.
The number of legal reforms that have taken place is incredible.
I would like to commend the government, commend the people, and ask that you please keep it up, because legal reforms alone, they kickstart the process.
But you need to follow them up with dedicated implementation, honest reviews, which is the process we're witnessing here.
And of course, reforms, reforms are unending.
They keep, you know, you keep refining the system until you join the League of Countries, because globally it has been discovered that the higher the GDP, the higher the level of equality in the country, the higher the GDP.
And Taiwan is no exception.
I would like to congratulate you.
In terms of performance, we are not here to reach the highest performing sector, but I would like to focus on the budget system, because gender responsive budgeting sits at the heart of implementation of CEDAW.
And your national machinery has done a great job.
But of course, we would always continue to demand more, because it is in the interest of all of society.
We observed gaps in certain critical sectors and the National Development Council was the most outstanding, with over 80% cuts in the budget.
And when gender equality is not linked to national development priorities, the society suffers, but the weak and the vulnerable suffer the most.
And society is as strong and as productive as the weakest group.
So efforts to deliver CEDAW is to scale up and increase the minimum standard for the weak in the society, so that the entire society can actually perform commendably.
And so the Ministry of Defense also is worthy of mention, because although they have achieved parity in terms of number of leaders at the leadership level, 50-50, that is not a mean, it's not an easy task.
However, we observed cuts in the budget and we do not see evidence of a gender inclusive security architecture in the country.
And so one of the things that we, in the context of the global security landscape, I think developing a national action plan on UNSCR 1325, which is reported through the CEDAW, is one of the areas that we think should be a focus,
so that the country is positioned to leverage the resources of both men, women, boys, girls, and the vulnerable.
Another observation that we had was mentioned at the opening, technology.
Digital governance is a new form of governance in the world, and Taiwan is really placed in a very strategic position to help to drive that change, if you would build on the mechanism that you have already started.
With Taiwan producing over 60% of AI or digital hardware, and the industries that drive that are located here, the resources that sustain the global AI revolution is Taiwanese.
It's indigenous to you, and therefore you have the opportunity to show the world how your inclusion and your commitment to CEDAW can actually also help the world in how AI unfolds.
And so that is one area that we observed.
We also looked at the future pact.
We talked about the future pact, because if you have signed up to CEDAW and you are implementing the SDGs, I'm sure Taiwan would be keenly following the future pact that was agreed in 2024.
It's setting out new pillars, new ways of working, a new UN system, and I believe that that is something that should drive the implementation of development and growth, particularly for women and girls in Taiwan.
I would like to stop here, because I wouldn't want to go alone into the substance, and so I will yield the floor to colleagues and then conclude at the end of the contribution by colleagues.
And I would like to start with no other than Professor Heisoo Shin.
She has been the architect.
No.
Because part of what we see is continuity, a vision that has borne a lot of fruits.
And so I would defer to your preference to come last, and maybe start with Marion, who is on the extreme right, and I hope we'll take a few minutes to focus on other critical sectors besides the ones I've mentioned.
Thank you very much.
Yes.
Thank you very much, Madam Chair of the International Review Committee, and good morning, Minister, good morning, and good morning to everybody here, all the distinguished guests and our civil society organization.
I want to echo the words and positions and sentiments put forward by Madam Chair, and to thank you so very much for inviting me to be here as part of this International Review Committee.
It has been my honor to engage with you, and I am so pleased to have had this opportunity and trust that the contribution that I have made as part of this International Review Committee has been valuable and meaningful for you all.
So I want to just look at a couple of the areas that I was tasked with reviewing and making interventions on, and the first one concerns articles one and two, and what I'd like to say here is that Taiwan has done incredible work in moving itself forward in this area of the
anti-discrimination draft legislation, which, however, has taken a very long time to actually come to fruition, perhaps 10 years or so, and so we're really encouraging you to commit to finalizing this anti-discrimination draft legislation.
I want to push it a little further and just to say that I think it's really important to look at the constitution of Taiwan and really ground the issue of anti-discrimination or discrimination against women in your constitution, and I say that because I can share with you from my own personal experience of my own country, the Bahamas, where our constitution permits discrimination.
On the basis of sex, it actually allows women to be discriminated against, and so as part of my review of Taiwan, I understand the position, and I really am encouraging you to ground it in a constitutional way so that any cascading or domestic legislation that flows out of the constitution, the constitution is the pinnacle of your legal architecture and has supremacy.
And so if you have anti-discrimination on the basis of sex within your constitution, I think you're home free in many ways, and so I share with you my own country's position.
We're still struggling with this issue of a constitutional guarantee for women in regard to a prohibition on the discrimination of sex and gender.
So I understand I'm with you, and I urge you to move beyond the point where you are now and to enact the anti-discrimination legislation and also review your constitution for the possibility of grounding it there.
And so that is what I would want to say about the anti-discrimination legislation.
It must also interface with the issues of intersectionality.
There are issues around women with disabilities, Indigenous women, the LBTI community that all need to be protected by anti-discrimination legislation, hopefully at the constitutional level also.
And so the intersectionality is really important that that become part of the definition that CEDAW has put forward in regard to discrimination and gender equality.
So I'll move on from there to talk a little bit about the National Human Rights Commission, which we engaged with.
And I'd like to thank the National Human Rights Commission officers for really helping with us and engaging with us on the issues that are presented.
Some of the challenges that are very evident in regard to how the Commission functions and where it wants to go and some of the impediments at this point in time.
And so, again, the push is for the NHRC to become compliant with the Paris Principles in regard to its independence and its full powers to have investigations, to compel public and private sectors to come before it, and to provide remedies in regard to violations of human rights.
And so this is still a task before the NHRC and a little comparison with my own country.
Again, we are struggling with the issue of even establishing an NHRC.
So you are way beyond and I'm encouraging you to take it to the next level of the independence of the National Human Rights Commission.
And this is really, really important and vital to the functioning of the governance of Taiwan in regard to protecting human rights violations.
And lastly, I just want to address very briefly the issue of gender based violence within the context of Taiwan.
And as you know, worldwide, this is an issue that it feels almost like an intractable issue, an issue that we cannot really get our hands around and make the kinds of dent and advances that are really necessary to the quality of women's lives.
And so I would urge Taiwan to really look at the structural and root causes of gender based violence.
It's really important to take it from that angle as profoundly and challenging as that is.
But you've got to see what about Taiwanese society and culture and traditions that are structurally embedded, that really contribute to the increasing domestic violence, the increasing sexual assaults on women and girls.
It's really important that you go that deeply as opposed to, well, in addition to awareness campaigns and programs, et cetera.
What is it at the root cause of gender based violence in your community?
And a very important part of that in anchoring it in CEDAW is that you recognize and identify the gender based violence is a form of discrimination as defined under CEDAW.
It is a form of discrimination and needs to be combated under the ages of discrimination against women and girls.
And so I encourage you to look at it in terms of the root causes and also the definition and understand and know that each and every gender based violence is a form of discrimination against women and girls.
And I think I'll leave it there.
I have taken a good bit of time and I've really enjoyed this engagement and understanding of Taiwanese society.
And again, thank you for having me and I am honored to engage with you.
Thank you so much.
Professor Naiklas, if you will.
Thank you.
Esteemed Minister, thank you.
Esteemed Minister, Madam Chair, ladies and gentlemen, it is an honor to be back here as an independent expert.
I was also here for the 2022 review and it is really good to see that progress has been made and the work is moving forward.
When I have this perspective of looking back a little bit to the earlier discussions, I make the note that we actually this time have been dealing partly with old issues but also with some new issues,
which I think really shows that the gender perspective is being taken into account also in new areas, especially when we discuss socioeconomic empowerment of women,
which is Article 13 in the CEDAW Convention, we have quite extensively been discussing trade agreements.
And we very much have welcomed the fact that the government has declared that clearly that gender equality considerations should be taken into account in trade negotiations.
This is very important. Trade negotiations, they have to do with credit, they have to do with investment, they have to do with public procurement, where a big amount of taxpayers' money is spent.
And it's very clear that the question of what are the terms and conditions for all these trade agreements and the international trade, it has a huge impact on national level, also on gender equality.
So what we are proposing in our report where we really value this commitment from the government, but we think that this activity, the gender considerations, should be taken into account in perhaps more comprehensive
and systematic manner than at present. And we also propose concretely to appoint the gender focal point on trade to coordinate these activities and also impact assessment in this field.
So this is, I think, a new opening which I think is important and I hope that the government is moving forward in this area.
Then, of course, when we have been working here, we are also dealing with old problems which we saw last time and which we can see that have been discussed very many times.
And this is not a unique case for Taiwan. When the UN system is examining member states, we see that there are some problems which are very difficult and very persisting.
Here, I can't resist to take up the very important thing about the issue of combining family obligations with work responsibilities and participation in public life.
Here, the SEDAW Convention Article 11.2C is very clear. It states that the state shall take appropriate measures to enable parents to combine family obligations with work responsibilities and participation in public life, in particular through promoting the establishment and development of a network of child care facilities.
We know that this issue of combination of work and family is very crucial in Taiwan because the birth rate in Taiwan is exceptionally low.
And this is, I think, the review committee sees this as a kind of national crisis problem which has to be solved and taken very seriously.
And we see that there is not lack of understanding that this is a problem. We see that many departments in the government is dealing with this problem.
But our impression is that this problem is perhaps dealt with in a little bit of a piecemeal way.
And we think that since this is such an important issue, it should be dealt with perhaps in a really extraordinary manner in some kind of national inclusive way where all stakeholders could take part.
And also, I think, the business life and employers should be involved. This is not a problem only for the social sector. This is a problem for the whole society and for the future of Taiwan.
So we think that you should really try to take a new overall comprehensive approach on this issue and really aim for establishing effective, accessible and to establish affordable, high quality, universal and nonprofit public child care services
as part of a program to really measure this problem. Also, there are other consistent problems. One is the issue of equal pay for work of equal value.
We have been dragging with this for quite a time. We have a problem with your legislation. We think it's not fully up to the CEDAW standard because the issue of equal value is not clearly defined in your legislation.
And these issues, I hope that although they seem to be difficult, improvement can be made. And one way of dealing with this is really to increase transparency when it comes to wages so that people know what wages are paid.
Then they can also, perhaps, women can demand equal pay. I leave it here. And I thank you once more for this adventure to be here in Taiwan. I think it is very important work which you are doing. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Nicholas. We will now go to the extreme of the table and I will yield the floor to Professor Netizia Bonifaz.
Thank you, Chair. I thank you all for being part of this important dialogue on the rights of Taigoneses women in this very special meeting. I want to congratulate you on all the progress you have made.
I'm going to present the main points from political participation, health, and marginalized rights. About parity, it's very important to achieve the 50-50 parity goal in line with CEDAW General Reclamation 40.
It's also important to provide incentives to political parties to enhance women's participation in the electoral process and implement training courses to promote women's leadership.
Also provide comprehensive support measures for women with disabilities to participate in political and public life. About health, we recommend to take steps to ensure that all women in Taiwan enjoy sexual and reproductive health and rights.
Especially for those in rural and remote areas. Improve health care services for women with disabilities and older women, especially in rural and remote areas. Ensure the meaningful participation of diverse groups of women and civil society in health policy making.
We recommend also about reproductive technology that the government take steps to permit single women and lesbians to access in vitro fertilization under the Assist Reproductive Technology Act.
About rural and marginalized women, we think that it's necessary to accelerate policies aimed at narrowing the inequality gaps between women living in rural and urban areas.
Finally, about elder people, about digital connection, we consider that it's necessary to accelerate access to technology for indigenous women and women living in rural areas.
And finally, we think that the government should strengthen policies regarding health care, social security, and services for older women. Thank you Cher, thank you all.
Thank you very much, Professor Laetitia. I will now turn to Professor Hei Sushin. You have the floor, please.
Thank you, Chair, for taking my request. Good morning.
Good morning, everyone.
This room is very familiar to me.
Most of you are very familiar to me.
This process is very familiar to me because I have been the regular person for the last almost 20 years.
I have been reviewing CEDAW implementation, but also I have been involved in the other treaty implementation, the International Covenant on Economic, Social, and Cultural Rights.
Taiwan is like a second home to me now.
Thank you for that.
Thank you for all your very well organized proceedings, good hospitality.
I feel home, you know, in Taipei.
So thank you for that.
But today, I have to talk about some not so well organized part of your society, and I will raise mainly in two areas.
First is regarding marriage and family life, which is very important for women's everyday life because women's lives move around the family and home.
So I want to point out that the Constitutional Court and the importance of it was already raised by my colleague Marion.
And there have been a Constitutional Court ruling three years ago already regarding how marriage can be resolved.
So we are talking about divorce.
And there was a Constitutional Court ruling which I read, you know, regarding that now the spouse who is at fault can also request divorce and can be granted.
And the Constitutional Court said that, well, the government should come up with legal amendments within two years to take up, you know, measures on related areas, which has not done yet.
So I think it needs some real action, you know, as soon as possible.
And I want to remind you that the Constitutional Court added there should be supplementary measures while granting divorce, the right to claim divorce to the at fault spouse.
The Constitutional Court said that there should be measures to safeguard the rights and interests of faultless or disadvantaged spouses.
For example, by reasonably raising the proportion of residual property allocated to the other spouse.
These are from the wordings of the ruling requiring the at fault spouse to pay higher maintenance, bear a greater share of child support or assume increased liability for damages or other negative effects arising from divorce.
And this is because it is necessary for timely and effective legal protection and remedies as well as fair substantive compensation.
So this review committee sees that there is a great vacuum because you didn't come up with legal measures yet, which is necessary.
So that is what we have recommended in our conclusions and recommendations regarding alimony, regarding division of residual marital property, child support.
And one thing the committee would like to emphasize is that alimony should not be tied with remarriage or child support because alimony is very important because women have been devoted to her most of her life, you know, for the family and care work for the family members.
Tying with this family issue, I see the committee sees another problem regarding another constitutional ruling for the ancestor worship guilds, which is still contain discriminatory aspects.
You know, there is a deep traditional patriarchal tradition surrounding this ancestor worship guilds, and the committee would like to see that Taiwan could or can get rid of these remaining aspects of traditional discriminatory discriminatory practices regarding ancestral
worship. So the guilds, whether it was formed before or whether it has internal regulation or not, women should be able to join and exercise the right as well as duties.
You know, you will need every member of the family because of the shrinking population to have the proper worship for the ancestors.
So that's one big area of family marriage equality.
Another area I would like to point out is regarding trafficking and sexual exploitation of women.
In this regards, Taiwan has a history which is shared by other Asian countries, including my own country, the Republic of Korea, the history of so-called comfort women, military sexual slavery.
This is connected to the current day Security Council Resolution 1325 on women, peace and security.
We now see wars are happening in Ukraine, in Iran, in many parts of the world.
And it is especially women and children who suffer trafficking and sexual exploitation in addition to the deaths and then collapsing and then fighting, etc.
So your history of military sexual slavery by Japan should be remembered, documented, maintained, taught, commemorated by the government because it is part of Taiwan's history that should never be repeated.
And that is what we should learn.
And the committee saw that it is not properly done in Taiwan.
So there should be revived teaching materials in the curriculum, as well as public commemoration, museum on women's history, including the comfort women issue, and then adequate support for the civil society who are doing all this, you know, instead of the government.
So we hope to see this change can be introduced in terms of your policy regarding the comfort women.
We know that there is no surviving comfort women in my country.
There are still about five who are all in very old age.
So we have to maintain in relation to that.
I also raised the current day nowadays sex trafficking, which is the issue of sex trade, which is a big problem and then left in vacuum because the law is not working and there is stigmatization.
And, you know, these women stay in that sex industry because she needs help, because they need help, because there are reasons, root causes.
It's not, you know, their fault.
So there should be all kinds of necessary assistance given in terms of health, education, welfare, alternative livelihood.
So we included that issue in our recommendation.
Of course, we cannot present here all the points in the recommendations.
So I hope that this will be, you know, widely disseminated.
I think the chair will talk about it.
But I hope that through this kind of review exercise, I think this is a good effort for Taiwanese government, people, everybody in Taiwan understands the issue and work together.
I think that's the message.
I don't know whether I can come the next round, but I would be happy to see much development and improvement until the next time.
Thank you very much.
Thank you very much, Professor Hesu, for not only the context, the background, but the encouragement, recognizing that the cost of inequality is very high.
And in certain areas we have actually requested that the government should calculate, compute the economic costs either of violence, of unpaid care work,
of services that are provided to the elderly, to people with disabilities, so that we can have a full understanding of why we invest in gender equality.
And before I hand over, I think there are certain areas that we also need to put on the table.
One of them is if you have heard from colleagues, we have quoted constitutional reviews, legislative reviews.
But the reality is that the effectiveness of CEDAW is moving from the jury to de facto.
That is, you move from the laws and your constitutional and legal and policy provisions to actually the lived experiences of women, men, boys and girls.
And that is why the issue of decentralization is so important.
It was something that came up. We know you have a law, you have the CEDAW incentive plan for municipalities, but this has just been a sitting law.
And we're asking that you activate this through the cities for CEDAW model.
It's a framework that is working in other parts of the world for countries that have not ratified like the United States and for countries who have ratified the CEDAW,
because it's a way of making CEDAW real and not just a paper document that you can within a city address safety issues, economic issues,
livelihood issues, protection issues and make the city safer and better equipped to deal with, you know, building resilience,
because where you have where women thrive, where the young people thrive, the societies grow.
And so the cities for CEDAW is an area that we think is in the recommendation and something that you already have in the law,
but it speaks to the need to activate the law. And in doing that, the other issue is ownership,
because CEDAW does not belong to the Department of Gender Equality or to Minister Mingsing.
It belongs to everybody. And we're asking that through engagement with critical and core sectors,
you actually can involve the private sector to ensure that you have this whole of society approach to delivering a CEDAW.
And the best way to do it is through temporary special measures, measures that you take.
You pilot them, you test them, you amend them, you refine them, and then you legalize them and you track and follow.
And of course, the last is a follow up mechanism, because without a regular, I know you have a follow up,
but we're asking that you extend, strengthen and deepen your follow up so that it's not only for the Department of Gender Equality.
It is for the municipalities. It is for the civil society themselves to say what they are doing so that at the end of the day,
what we have is a stronger, more robust society where inequalities are reduced
and the human capital base of the country keeps rising because of the level of investment you pay into it,
because of the level of engagement of different sectors of society,
and because of the resilience that is built by the society to address future shocks,
global warming, environmental disaster, climate change, technology, mining.
These are all unforeseeable challenges.
And when you build a stronger society, you can leverage all of the human capacity of your society to do a better job.
I am so thankful to be, this is my second time, and it has only gotten better.
I thank you for the courtesies extended, for the opportunity, for the privilege.
And I do sincerely look forward to working with you.
In my country, we are already moving into the private sector.
We have a public procurement, affirmative procurement policy, which is a waiting signature in the Ministry of Justice.
And the target there is that 40% of all public procurement will be inclusive.
35% for women, 30% for women, 10%, 20% for women, 10% for the youth.
And then you have the veterans, the elderly, and people with disabilities sharing the remaining 5%,
with women cutting across all categories.
And this is to help us to develop gender positive, large scale businesses,
so that opportunity is broadened for everybody, dependency reduces in society,
and then we can open new avenues of investment.
Thank you very, so I want to really, really express my gratitude.
Thank you.
And I look forward to any opportunity to work with departments and agencies here to drive the CEDAW agenda.
Thank you very much.
And next comes the important part.
The International Review Committee would like to hand the concluding recommendations and observations over to the ROC Taiwan government.
And for that, we'd like to have Minister Lin to come to the front.
And of course, all the members of the International Review Committee would you please also come to the front.
We would like to have the five members of the International Review Committee to come to the front to hand the concluding recommendations and observations over to the ROC Taiwan government.
Okay.
Yes.
Firstly, just stand just a little bit apart from each other so that we can hand the report over to the ROC Taiwan government.
Please hand the report over to the ROC Taiwan government.
And now for the group photo, you may stand closer to each other.
Okay.
Look at the camera in front of you.
All right.
Can we do this?
Thumbs up.
The review is done finally.
We can do this pose.
Okay.
And now would you return to your seats?
We go over time just a little bit, but we still want to see if there are one or two questions from our audience today.
We would like to thank our five reviewers for their recommendations and words of encouragement and thank all of you for your participation in the interest of time.
We're going to very quickly go into QA from the media, and please keep it short when you ask the questions and keep it to the point so that our reviewers may answer.
I hope we can finish the QA session in 10 minutes.
We will take three questions from three reporters on site.
Doesn't seem to be any questions.
If there are no questions, that's all right.
I would like to take this opportunity to speak on behalf of the head of the government delegation to respond to some of the issues raised by our reviewers.
I have noted all of them, and I will do my best to require that the government do this.
I think equal pay for equal work is something we emphasized, and this time our reviewers mentioned something even more important.
It's not just in the form, but value.
It needs to be equal pay for equal value, equal value with equal pay.
With the equal value of in the work that they do, they should receive equal pay and not just in the same form of work.
This is very important.
When we are calculating what equal value means, we can think about the unpaid care work or care provided in the families or domestic care.
When we calculate what that cost is, will we really be able to see whether or not the same kind of work has the same value and are receiving equal pay?
I think these are very important.
This is something that I took away from this week as a very important issue, and I would like to thank our reviewers for providing us with this recommendation so that we can work harder to improve this.
And that involves the care economy in terms of the care for the family and for the society.
And its economic implications are, I think, things we need to take into consideration.
The calculation of the cost of the national economy should be included, not just consider it as an unpaid service.
And I think this is something we really learned from our reviewers, and I am mentioning it here.
And Professor Xing would also like to provide additional comments.
So I'm going to give floor to her.
But my last comments, in addition to express our gratitude to our five members of IRC, I would like to see you more frequently in the future in Taiwan.
And please feel free to pass the word on to your friends because you are important opinion leaders on the international stage and in the U.N.
So please help us to bring our voices from Taiwan to international society so we can be treated fairly.
Thank you very much.
I would like to say a few words, not comment, but actually a suggestion, because this last day press conference, I've been attending now nine times, you know,
five times for CEDAW and then four times for the ICCPL, ICSCR.
And I know that all the time pressure preparation, we worked until almost 10 o'clock last night to finalize our conclusions and recommendations.
And then, of course, then it was sent to the Department of Gender Equality and then being translated overnight.
And then while we were on the stage, we were given clean text of English for ourselves.
So I know it's very difficult, but it is for the public governments as well as civil society, but for the press to understand not only the points that we emphasized, you know,
for five of us, but I think that should be distributed, the paper, yeah, because it was already translated.
And then we'll not take much time to print and then, you know, give out to people who are here at least.
I know it will be uploaded on the website later, but it would be, I think, helpful if all of you receive, although it's not complete.
You know, there might be some editorial changes needed, but not in content.
So I would like to ask the government that for the next review, maybe at the press conference, everybody when enters the room can receive a hard copy so that while each of us presents our points,
maybe read through and then might have some questions because it's difficult to ask for the press to ask questions just listening to what we are saying.
So that would be my request. I hope it would be accommodated so that you have at least a hard copy of what we are recommending, which will be the basis for the next four years implementation.
But this this is all content. This all contains the hard work of the government, civil society for the last four years, you know, and then and then for the recommendation from the committee.
So, please. Thank you.
Thank you.
Yes. So for the next time, four years later, we will try our best to have the hard copies ready for our journalists.
So at least they can have a copy of the English original English version.
Oh, yes, they already have the English version, but not the Chinese translation version.
I think everything have you done for the conclusion for the shadow, but I would like to know one question about the BT because they have to get the surgery.
And then can get the idea.
So I would like to know what about your opinions about every BT because I didn't see the view in the conclusion.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for your question.
I hope I understood the question.
You were talking about LBTI and access to identification.
And if you look, if you have a copy, you will see that what when we talked about the definition of discrimination and amending and providing constitutional guarantees, that's really where it begins.
Because when your definition of equality is clear, then the role and place of all groups within your society is clarified and they will not be discriminated or refused an identity or barriers to them securing identity will be removed.
So it is addressed in that area.
We also talked about gender stereotypes and we have here in paragraph 29.
We specifically talk about removing barriers that adopted comprehensive policy strategy and program to address discriminatory gender stereotypes and particular attitudes deeply embedded in social structures for many categories.
And we ask that you train the media, train public officials, the judiciary to promote gender responsive media, because it is through the media that a lot of bias and stereotypes is reinforced or reinvented.
And we target particularly vulnerable groups, including the LBTI community.
And I'm sure when Professor Leti was speaking, you also heard about the ability to help.
Let me read precisely what the recommendation says with regards to LBTI.
We realize that consent is denied to LBTI women to be able to secure abortion when they are married.
Those are areas of concern to LBTI groups of women.
And we also find that in the area of adoption and reproductive technology, you also find that LBTI women also face some kind of discrimination.
So what you find is it is not just the identity card that is the discrimination that LBTI women face.
They face in many areas, just like migrant women, elderly women, indigenous women, all these aspects of discrimination that when your law is reformed,
you will find that they will have access to services, access to education, to opportunity to work.
And that really is what the convention is all about.
That all groups of women within the society do not face increased barriers to be able to participate in the social, economic, and political life of the country.
I hope this answers your question.
And I don't know if any committee member wants to add.
No?
Thank you.
Our members of IRC, I think they still have other engagements with Legislative Yuan in Control Yuan.
So we have to conclude our press conference today so they can have ample time to go to Legislative Yuan to attend press conference there.
Again, I would like to thank the five IRC members and also our audience members from the press and civil society.
Thank you very much for your participation.
This is a joint work of the government and also the civil society.
I hope we can show a better performance four years later.
Thank you very much.
Thank you all.
That's it for our press conference today.
We're going to continue to work together and create a world that champions human rights and gender equality.
Thank you again for your time.
Have a good day, everybody.